A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Education and Research, Public Education, Office Files of Marjorie Martus FA714
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Education and Research, Public Education, Office Files of Marjorie Martus
1962-1968, 1971-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Martus, Marjorie
Ford Foundation
FA714
2.66 Cubic Feet
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been transferred to the appropriate collections. Crossreference sheets located within the folders, denote the new locations of these items which are listed in the back of this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
Marjorie Martus, Ford Foundation Program Officer in the Division of Education and Research, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1958 until 1982. During this period, she held the positions as a research assistant, program assistant, assistant program officer, and program officer.
Marjorie Martus was born July 13, 1923. She received her B.A. degree in 1945 from Antioch College. She did additional course work at Columbia University, New York University, and the Bank Street College of Education.
Prior to Martus' career with the Ford Foundation, she held the following positions:
1945-1946, Office of War Information, Information Specialist
1946-1948, U.S. Department of State, Divisional Assistant, Division of International Exchange of Persons
1948-1954, United States Government, Technical Assistance Specialist; Economic Cooperation Administration, The Hague, The Netherlands
1954-1955, Douglas Williams Associates, Office Manager; Interviewer
1955-1956, Milliontex, Inc., Officer Manager
1956-1957, Rockefeller Bros. Fund, Staff Assistant
Following her retirement from the Ford Foundation, Miss Martus was employed by the School of Education at Stanford University.
Scope and Contents
The Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives in 1982.
The seven boxes of correspondence and reports which constitute the Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus, document her activities and a number of those of the Education Program for the years 1962 to 1968; and from 1971 to 1975.
The papers include material related to Ford Foundation educational activities and projects; and correspondence with Foundation colleagues, and individuals in academic, grantee and other organizations.
The papers are broad in scope, but are rather disappointingly superficial, especially in light of Miss Martus' activity and reputation. It is recommended that the researcher consult the files of grants for which Miss Martus served as Responsible Program Officer, a list of which is included in the appendix to this register.
Arrangement
The Education and Research/Public Education Papers of Marjorie Martus are divided into two series:
I. Correspondence Files, 1962-1968, 1971-1975
II. Subject Files, 1962-1968
Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Martus' office.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Correspondence Files, 1962-1968, 1971-1975; I; 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence Files (1962-1968; 1971-1975), contains correspondence generated by Miss Martus during her years at the Foundation. The correspondence is divided into two subseries:
  A. Chronological Files, which are arranged in reverse calendar order; and
  B. Alphabetical Files, which are arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent. Within each Alphabetical File folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order
  - Chronological Files, A
    - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
    - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13-20)
    - 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25-36)
    - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 37-48)
    - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 49-56)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 57-60)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 61-72)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 73-84)
    - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 85-96)
    - 1965 (Box 5, Folder 97-108)
    - 1964 May-November (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - 1964 January-April (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - 1962 July-1963 December (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Alphabetical Files, B
    - Chilman, C., 1970 February-June (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Deutsch, M., 1965-1966 December (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Farmer, J., 1965 May-1966 August (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - Gray, S., 1971 October-1972 June (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - Guttentag, M., 1968 November-1969 August (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - Hobson, A., 1967 November-1968 February (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Hovet, M., 1966 March-1967 March (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Keeve, P., 1967 January-1968 January (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Miller, D., 1965 October-1966 April (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Mohan, B., 1967 December-1968 February (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Nicholls, J., 1967 August-September (Box 6, Folder 122)
- Subject Files, 1962-1968; II; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
  Series II, Subject Files (1962-1968), consists of correspondence and other material as it relates to each topic. The files are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Arizona Laboratory, 1967 October-December (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Benjamin Franklin High School, 1966 April-June (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Carolinas and Virginia Regional Laboratory, 1967 November-1968 July (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Child Development, 1964 December-1965 January (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Dyslexia, 1964 September-1967 June (Box 6, Folder 127-128)
  - Early Childhood Education - DRAFT Material, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 129-134)
  - Freyburg Academy (Reading Research Institute), 1962 June-1966 March (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Institute for Developmental Studies, 1966 September-1968 June (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Language Consultants - BA-HA, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Language Consultants - JO-SE, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Language Development Study, 1967 January-1968 April (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Lexington School for the Deaf, 1965 January-1967 February (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - National Institute for Mental Health, 1964 December-1968 August (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1969 January (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 143-144)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1968 December-1969 January (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, 1968 December-1969 January (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Ohio State University Research Consortium, 1967 December-1968 May (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Pre-School Television, 1967 April-1968 April (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Publication Orders, 1966 October-1968 June (Box 7, Folder 149-150)
  - System Development Corporation, 1964 September-1968 January (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Team Teaching, 1964 October-1966 April (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Research and Development Centers - United States, 1967 March-1969 November (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - School Improvement Work Conference, San Francisco, 1967 January 3-7 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Social Science Research Council Conference, Chicago, February 7-9, 1966, 1965 June-1966 February (Box 7, Folder 155)